玄黄端现 太极混沌如鸡蛋
ln the beginning, there was darkness...
随着轰的一声
and then, bang...
时间 空间和物质
giving birth to an endless expanding existence...
of time, space, and matter.
现在 所见超乎我们的想象
Now, see further than we've ever imagined...
超越了客观认知极限
beyond the limits of our existence...
那地方我们称之为"宇宙"
in a place we call "The Universe."
混沌壮观
Chaotic and breathtaking...
它们的美丽形成于虚无的空间
their beauty forms from the emptiness of space.
星云是星系的一切 而恒星却不是
Nebulas are everything in the galaxy that stars are not.
飘渺的物质 时而聚拢
Wisps of matter, at times coming together...
时而散开
at others, flying apart...
朦胧的面纱 翻腾的云团
filmy veils, billowing masses...
有些昏暗 有些闪烁着明亮的色彩
some dark, some glowing in brilliant colors...
许多形状已见怪不怪
many taking the shapes of things that are eerily familiar.
有趣的是人们看到星云
lt's interesting when people look at nebulas...
就会开始产生幻觉
they sort of start seeing things in it.
既非恒星 也非行星 它们才是星系之王
Neither stars nor planets, they are the crownjewels of the galaxy.
宇宙展现了星云里恒星的生死
The universe reveals its awesome display...
以及创世循环叹为观止的展示
of stellar birth, death, and the cycle of creation inside the nebulas.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://cmct.cc
影片压制:春树  字幕来源:五羊皮  调校:御雪寒狼  招募Q号:76846146
[历史频道] 第二季 第十四集 星云
[History Channel] The UniverseⅡ 14of19 Nebulas
这是有史以来拍到的最著名的太空照片之一
lt is one of the most famous space photographs ever taken.
一如哈勃太空望远镜所见
As seen by the Hubble Space Telescope...
它显示出创造之柱
it shows the Pillars of Creation...
巨大的尘埃和气体柱有7光年之长
massive columns of dust and gas seven light-years long.
它们之大 柱子只是其很小一部分
As big as they are, the Pillars are just a small part...
距离地球6500光年的巨大星际育婴室
of an immense stellar nursery 6,500 light-years from Earth...
称为天鹰星云
called the Eagle Nebula.
各种星云散落在繁星之间
Nebulas of all kinds are scattered among the stars everywhere...
是我们乃至其它星系间最壮观的景象
and are among the most spectacular sights...in ours or any galaxy.
星云美丽动人 无一例外
Nebulae are beautiful, all of them.
它们确实夺人眼球
They really strike the eye.
根据云的希腊词汇 星云就是
From the Greek word for cloud, nebulas are just that...
星际气体和尘埃的云 肉眼难得一见
clouds of interstellar gas and dust, rarely visible to the naked eye.
然而 通过空间和地面的望远镜
But with telescopes in space and on Earth...
它们的美容昭然若揭
their beauty is revealed.
闪亮 反射或遮掩星系的光辉
Glowing, reflecting, or obscuring the galaxy's light...
它们是恒星的出生之地
they are regions where stars are born...
丧命之地 爆发之地
where stars die, and where explosions...
是时空结构的刑场
rack the very fabric of space-time.
星云的形状千姿百态
Nebulas have fantastic shapes...
犹如夏季的云彩
like clouds in the sky on a summer day.
它们产生的意象往往惟妙惟肖
They often evoke imagery that hits very close to home.
似花
lmages of flowers...
似虫
images of insects...
似人
images of people.
有趣的是 人们观察星云时
lt's interesting when people look at nebulas.
就像是做罗沙哈测验(让人解释墨水点绘的图形以判断其性格)
lt's like a Rorschach test.
他们会开始产生幻觉
They sort of start seeing things in it.
尽管 星云都已经贴上了天文学的编目
Although nebulas are labeled with numbers from astronomical catalogs...
但是 好多被创造性地以其位置和形状而冠名
many also have names inspired by their locations or shapes.
并不困难 比如
lt's not difficult, for instance...
来看一下为何这叫做蝴蝶星云
to see why this is called the Butterfly Nebula...
这被称为马头星云
or this is known as the Horse Head Nebula.
这样的例子不胜枚举
The list goes on.
猎户星云
The Orion Nebula...
鬼头星云
the Ghost Head Nebula...
刺魟星云
the Stingray Nebula...
旋涡星云
the Helix Nebula...
猫眼星云
the Cat's Eye Nebula...
北美星云
the North American Nebula...
鹈鹕星云
the Pelican Nebula.
星云的千姿百态
The astonishing forms nebulas take...
使其成为了星系中的亮丽风景线
make them the tourist attractions of the galaxy.
如果你举家坐上飞碟
lfyou've got the family in a flying saucer...
想漂流银河
and you're careening through the Milky Way...
想寻找有趣的休憩之处 就去星云吧
looking for an interesting rest stop, you're going to go to a nebula.
宛如地球上的旅游胜地
Like tourist attractions on Earth...
遥远的星云吸引着我们一游为快
faraway nebulas entice us for a closer look.
哥们 这是郊游
Man, it's a hike.
夜空中最大的诱惑之一
One of the prime attractions in the night sky...
就是大猎户星云
is the great Orion Nebula...
是你肉眼能看到的极少数星云之一
one of the very few nebulas you can see with the naked eye.
晴朗之夜 它看上去就像是猎户之剑里的一颗模糊的星星
On a clear night, it appears as a fuzzy star in the sword of Orion...
那或许是空中最容易辨认的星座
probably the most recognizable constellation in the sky.
猎户星云是银河系里恒星形成最活跃的地区
The Orion Nebula is the most active area of starformation in our galaxy.
它照亮夜空且别无所求
lt lights up the sky like nothing else.
所以这是个大款
So this is a big one.
对星云来说这是好莱坞的标记
ln terms of nebulas, this is the Hollywood sign.
去旅游胜地一游的理由
And the reason why travelers want to get close to tourist attractions...
与天文学家仔细观察星云的理由并无二致
is the same as why astronomers want a closer look at nebulas.
大家争相举起相机
They each want to take photos.
毕竟是旅游 无论在人间还是天堂
After all, tourism, whether earthly or astronomical...
就是到处留影
is all about the pictures.
星云的照片占有非常特殊的地位
Photographs of nebulas occupy a real special niche...
非常重要的地位 我是这么认为的
a very important niche, l think...
因为它们真的登峰造极
because they really do sit at the pinnacle...
集艺术与科学于一身
the confluence of art and science.
当然拍摄出色的星云照片
Of course, getting good pictures of a nebula...
不仅仅是对准和咔嚓的问题
isn't just a matter of point and click.
在圣地亚哥北部山区
ln the mountains north of San Diego...
一个业余观星团登上崎岖之路
a group of amateur stargazers have an especially tough road to follow...
去追寻星云 拍摄精美的照片
in seeking out nebulas and taking great pictures.
长途跋涉来这里总是有回报的
lt is always worth the long drive to come out here.
星空下的夜晚 即使我没有拍成照
Night under the stars, even if l don't do any imaging...
也是值得的 就为了一睹在家看不到的东西
is worth it just to see what l can't see from home.
一旦装备复杂到了这个份上
When the equipment is this complex...
这帮粉丝就不仅仅是拍照了
these enthusiasts aren't just taking pictures.
在这里话题就是成像
Here, the word is "imaging"...
他们追逐的目标就是星云
and theirfavorite targets are the nebulas.
就为了看上一眼
Just being able to look at them...
想象一下气体云里的情况
and imagine what's going on out there in that gas cloud...
就为了能一睹星星形成之地的景象
and being able to see a sense ofwhere stars are forming...
那就是一种非凡的感官享受
it's just a great kind of a sensory experience to have.
除了便携式望远镜外
ln addition to their portable telescopes...
这帮人还建起了一座复杂的永久天文台
the group has also built a complex of permanent observatories.
在圆顶里 建有他们20吋大口径望远镜
lnside the enclosure housing their big twenty-inch telescope...
杰出的天文摄影家艾伦·斯莫伯恩
accomplished astrophotographer Alan Smallbone...
将一架天文相机装上目镜
attaches a special astrocamera to the eyepiece.
它准备拍摄猎户星云
He's preparing to image the Orion Nebula.
它对我是个极具挑战性的对象 因为它有很亮的区域
lt's a very challenging object to me because it has very light areas...
有很明亮的区域
it has very bright areas...
有很暗的区域
it has very dark areas...
是个很难精准拍摄的项目
and it's a very difficult item to photograph accurately.
如今的天文摄影家所使用的数码相机
The digital cameras used by today's astrophotographers...
仿真人眼的色觉
emulate colorvision in the human eye itself.
视网膜上有三种圆锥细胞
There are three kinds of cone cells on the retina...
分别感应蓝 绿 红光
each sensitive to either blue, green, or red light.
那就是这些颜色被认为是光的三原色的原因
That's why those colors are considered the primary colors of light.
但是天文相机里的视网膜
But the retina of an astrocamera...
是一片计算机芯片 只感应黑白两色
is a computer chip sensitive only to black and white.
因此 对于彩色照片来说 会用上红 绿 蓝色的滤镜
So for color photos, it uses red, green, and blue filters...
每一种颜色至少要拍上一次
taking at least one shot with each one.
这通常被称为三原色技术
lt's often called the RGB technique...
是产生较为本色的标准
and is standard for producing more natural color.
在摄取猎户星云时
ln capturing the Orion Nebula...
斯莫伯恩持续曝光了5分钟
Smallbone takes time exposures lasting five minutes...
分别用上了三种滤镜
through each of the three filters.
然而 星云非常暗淡 难以获得最佳照片
But nebulas are so dim that for the best photos...
他通常需要无数次曝光
he often needs dozens of exposures...
时间长达14个小时
with times totaling as much as fourteen hours.
没人会说这活不难
No one ever said this was easy.
天文成像非常枯燥 因为其非常耗时
Astroimaging can be very tedious because it's very time-consuming.
需要长时间坐着
lt involves long periods of time where you're sitting...
观望相机 监视器不停地跟踪
waiting for the camera, and the monitor's just tracking...
除了坐等 别无选择
and there's really nothing you can do except sit and wait.
随后斯莫伯恩将原始相片集中到电脑里
Later, Smallbone stacks the raw images on his computer.
在这里红 蓝 绿点的各种组合
There, the different combinations...
其运作就如彩电
of red, blue, and green dots work just like a color TV...
创造出光谱中的各种颜色
to create every other hue in the spectrum.
打开快门后数小时
Hours afterfirst opening the shutter...
猎户星云在屏幕上呈现出它的本色
the Orion Nebula appears in its natural colors on the screen...
肉眼不具备看见的感应能力
as no human eye has the sensitivity to see it.
存在的各种引人注目的星云图像
The striking images of these and other nebulas...
基本说明了天文摄影术的不可或缺性
demonstrate the essential reason astrophotography is indispensable...
就星云而论
when it comes to the nebulas.
由于望远镜与相机的结合
The combination of a telescope and a camera...
实际上让你看到了星云构造里的细节
actually allows you to see details in structures in the nebulae...
那是肉眼无法看到的
that you couldn't see with your own eye...
因为它们太昏暗且太弥散了
because they're so faint and diffuse.
大猎户星云非常值得关注
The great Orion Nebula is well worth the attention it gets.
跨度15光年
Fifteen light-years across...
大团的云成分主要是氢
it is a massive cloud, made mostly of hydrogen.
它是所谓的产星区这一类星云的典型例子
lt is the quintessential example of the kind of nebula...known as a star-forming region.
它是诞生于银河系里的大质量恒星的摇篮
lt is the cradle of the most massive stars...that are born in our galaxy.
它是向我们行进的最近的例子
And it is the closest example of that process to us.
所以你看大猎户星云时
So when you look at the great Orion Nebula...
会看到恒星在孕育
you're looking at stars being born.
在猎户星云的数千颗婴儿恒星里
Among the thousands of infant stars in the Orion Nebula...
有四颗控制着星云的四个角
four of them dominate...
被称为猎户座四边形
the corners of a cluster called the Trapezium...
名字源自其梯形
for its trapezoidal shape.
它们庞大而炙热导致了闪亮的天文奇观
Massive and hot, they are responsible...for the brilliant astronomical display.
大猎户星云中央的四边形
The Trapezium in the center of the great Orion Nebula...
给了星座以能量
is what energizes it.
是它让星座变成了星云
lt's what makes it a nebula.
如果没有四边形就只能是一片暗云
If you didn't have the Trapezium stars, it would be a dark cloud.
四边形里的辐射塑造了四周的气体
Radiation from the Trapezium stars sculpts the surrounding gas...
使其在光照下一片通亮
and causes it to glow with emitted light.
乘上飞船穿越猎户星云将会是怎样的情景？
What would it be like to fly through the Orion Nebula in a spacecraft?
可能会是这样的情景
lt might look like this...
一个非常精准的超级计算机模拟
a remarkably accurate supercomputer simulation...
基于哈勃太空望远镜的详细数据
based on detailed Hubble Space Telescope data...
建模者是范德比尔特大学的天文学家罗伯特·奥德尔
and modeled byVanderbilt University astronomer Robert O'Dell.
进入巨大的星云
Traveling into the gigantic cloud...
我们看到明亮的猎户座四边形四星
we see the four bright Trapezium stars...
其3D位置清晰可辨
their 3-D positions now clearly evident.
它们巨大的能量已经掏空了星云的中心
Their intense energy has hollowed out the nebula's center.
四边形四星非常耀眼
The Trapezium stars are so bright...
以至于我们看不清星云的其他部分
that they would blind us to the rest of the nebula...
如果我们的屏幕不放大的话 就看不清所有的细节
if ourview screen were not enhanced to show us all the details.
四散的暗珠
The dark globs scattered about...
称为[PROPLYD] 即原行星盘
called proplyds or protoplanetary disks...
是新生恒星周围的尘埃毯
are blankets of dust surrounding newly formed stars...
被四边形强大的星际风压缩成了水滴状
forced into teardrop shapes by energetic stellarwinds...from the Trapezium.
其中之一清晰地表明
One of them clearly shows...
环状碎片围绕着中央恒星
a ring of debris orbiting its central star...
有力地证明了新的行星系统正在形成
strong evidence that a new system of planets is forming.
我们离开猎户星云的路线
Our route out of the Orion Nebula...
向我们展示了从地球看它的角度
shows us the angle at which we see it from Earth.
然而 在1300光年以外
But at 1,300 light-years away...
它退缩成了我们视野里的一个小不点
it shrinks to a minor smudge in our field ofview.
想象一下在距离只有4光年的最近的恒星
lmagine how it would look at only four light-years...
所见到的情景
the distance to the nearest star.
猎户星云
The Orion Nebula...
如果我们距离猎户星云
ifwe were as close to the Orion Nebula...
如其最近的恒星那样 那么它就会明亮到
as the nearest star is to us, it would be so bright...
我们就不知道居然还会有夜空
that we wouldn't be aware of the dark sky.
我们就不会看到其它星星
We wouldn't see the other stars.
我们几乎不知道还有其它星系
We would almost not be aware of other galaxies...
只是因为它太明亮了
just because it would be so bright.
整个世界将只是猎户星云和太阳
The whole world would be the Orion Nebula and the Sun.
幸运的是 我们偏居星系一隅
Fortunately, we live at a point in the galaxy...
在这里我们的望远镜和相机可以梳理天穹
where our telescopes and cameras can comb the heavens...
抖散这些珠宝-星云
to shake loose the gems we call nebulas.
共有五个大类
There are five major kinds.
恒星形成星云 比如被称为的HⅡregions猎户星云
Star-forming nebulas like Orion are called H-ll regions.
H-Ⅱ表现了稀薄的氢
H-ll describes the thin hydrogen...
受到恒星发出的光的激发
excited by hot stars to emit light.
在其他地方存在着反射星云
ln other places, there are reflection nebulas...
亮星驱散周围的气体
where the bright stars have driven away the surrounding gas...
留下尘埃反射星光
leaving mostly dust to reflect starlight.
行星状星云形成于普通恒星的垂死阶段
Planetary nebulas are formed...during the slow, dying stages of ordinary stars...
会在星系中产生一些最有趣的形状和颜色
and produce some of the most intriguing displays...of shape and color in the galaxy.
超新星残骸也是恒星消亡的残留物
Supernova remnants are also leftovers from stellar deaths...
不过是大质量恒星生命结束于巨大的爆炸之中
but from massive stars, which end their lives in immense explosions.
最后是暗星云
And finally, there are the dark nebulas...
星际气体和尘埃云
clouds of interstellar gas and dust...
被看见通常是因为它们在背后
visible usually because they appear in silhouette...
明亮的星云衬托下才表现出来
against the bright nebulas behind them.
迟早会有恒星在其中突然诞生
ln time, stars will burst into existence within them.
然而 星系里最原始的星云 气体尘埃云
But the very origin of the galaxy's clouds of stars, gas, and dust...
全都是最耐人寻味的现象
is the most intriguing phenomenon of all.
来自神秘的星际介质
Springing from the mysterious interstellar medium...
星云之谜就在于它们怎么能够
the riddle of the nebulas is how they can form...
形成于一无所有之中
from what is almost nothing at all.
在太空虚无缥缈间
Space, in its vast emptiness...
远不止眼前这些
has much more to it than meets the eye.
在太阳与邻居之间充满了中性星际介质[ISM]
Filling the distances between the Sun and all its galactic neighbors...is the neutral interstellar medium or lSM.
在我们打量星际间漆黑一片时
When we think about the blackness between stars...
有时 会以为没有什么东西而是真空一片
we sometimes think there's nothing there but the vacuum of space.
但是 实际上 即使所谓的真空
But actually, even the so-called vacuum of space...
也是充满了尘埃和气体
is full of dust and gas.
现在它相当的稀薄
Now, it's quite rarefied.
有多稀薄？
How rarefied?
或许比我们在地球上创造的真空还要真空
Perhaps better than the best vacuum...we can create on the planet Earth.
星际介质里的粒子
The particles in the interstellar medium...
九成是氢原子 一成是氦原子
are ninety percent hydrogen atoms, ten percent helium...
极微量的其他元素和细微的尘埃
and trace amounts of other elements and tiny specks of dust.
气体和尘埃的存在是明显的
Existence of the gas and dust is evident...
通过观察银河系里的恒星带
by looking at the Milky Way...
我们从地球看到的侧面像
the band of stars we see in the edge-on view...of our home galaxy from Earth.
在那儿黑暗的空间里似乎空无一物
There, the dark spaces seem to be empty...
然而事实上情况恰恰相反
but in reality, the opposite is true.
那些空间里并不缺乏恒星
Those spaces aren't devoid of stars.
它们实际上是尘埃 在我们与银河系的平面上
They're actually dust between us and the distant stars...
的遥远的恒星之间
in the plane of our galaxy...
阻挡了光线 你看到的是它们的身影
and they block that light, and you see them in silhouette.
气体尘埃的黑色通道
The black lanes of gas and dust...
表明星际介质以其最原始的形态
show us where the interstellar medium...
纠结在一起形成了星云
is clumping together to form nebulas in their most primeval form.
我们看到在背景恒星里的星云剪影
We see these dark nebulas as shadows against the background stars.
蛇星云距离650光年
The Snake Nebula is 650 light-years distant...
跨度3光年
and approximately three light-years across.
更暗的是巴纳德68
Even darker is Barnard 68...
以爱德华·埃莫森·巴纳德的名字命名
named for Edward Emerson Barnard...
他就是发现它的人
the astronomer who discovered it.
这种星云似乎遮挡身后的星光够深邃的了
Such nebulas may be deep enough..to block light from stars behind them...
但是 其中的气体尘埃 还是非常稀薄
but the gas and dust inside them is still very thin...
直至引力的作用提速为止
that is until gravity's work accelerates.
引力就是吸引力
Gravity is attractive.
从而大团的气体
As a consequence, we have lumps of gas...
无论其多么稀薄 一直被引力吸引着
no matter how rarefied, being attracted by gravity...
直到产生凝聚的核质团
until we have clumps of nuclear material condensing.
随着引力开始压缩气体
As gravity begins to compress the gas...
温度开始升高
it starts to heat up in temperature...
产生恒星的温度
creating the temperatures of a star.
新的恒星横空出世
The new stars burst into existence...
以其斑斓的光辉照亮了周遭
lighting up their surroundings with colorful brilliance.
残留的暗星云形成了鲜明的对照
Remaining dark nebulas stand out in stark contrast.
和亮星云一样它们的形状决定了其名字
Like bright nebulas, their shapes suggest names.
象鼻星云
The Elephant's Trunk Nebula...
椎状星云
the Cone Nebula...
火焰星云 它的明暗区域
and the Flame Nebula, where dark and light areas...
创造了空中最引人入胜的景象之一
create one of the sky's most dramatic images.
产星区的亮丽色彩
The brilliant colors of the star-forming regions...
缘自星云气体受到附近炙热的新星
come from nebular gases excited by invisible ultraviolet radiation...
发出的紫外线激发而成
from nearby hot new stars.
那些星发出的光 紫外光
The light, the ultraviolet light from those stars...
剥离了周围气体里的电子
is stripping offthe electrons in the gas in its immediate vicinity.
这些电子游荡数天乃至数周
These electrons float around for days orweeks...
最后找上裸露的质子
and then ultimately find a bare proton...
或其它正电荷的核子 于是它们跳上轨道
or other positively charged nucleus, and they'll hop on to orbits...
此时 就会发出光线
and as they do, they'll emit light.
罗切斯特大学 天文学家 亚当·弗兰克
At the University of Rochester, astronomerAdam Frank...
将星云里的气体激荡比作篮球比赛
compares the excitement of gases in a nebula to a basketball game.
篮球比赛真的是个好比喻
This basketball game is a real nice analogy...
尽管俗气 但对星云还是很贴切的
though earthbound, forwhat happens in a nebula.
场边 你观看罗切斯特大学对阵纽约大学
Down on the court, you got Rochester going up against NYU.
篮球运动员很像星云中心的恒星
The basketball players are a lot like the stars at the center of the nebula.
场上发生精彩时
When something exciting happens on the court...
你会看到大家群情激昂
you'll see the crowd getting all excited.
雀跃欢呼 释放能量
The crowd stands up, they cheer, they emit energy.
在这里是声能
ln this case it's sound energy...
而在星云里 就是光能
but in the nebula, it would be light.
情况完全一样
This is exactly the same thing that happens...
电子被剥离原子后
when an electron gets ripped off an atom...
游荡上一会
flies around for a while...
然后找上另一个原子与之合并
and then finds another atom to recombine with...
同时释放出能量
and emits energy at the same time.
新星在星云里诞生时
As new stars are born within the nebulas...
有时会发出壮观的喷射
they sometimes shoot out spectacularjets.
这个有3万亿英里长
This one is three trillion miles long.
喷射是星云凭着自身的条件
Thejets are nebulas in their own right...
通过气体尘埃云的旋转产生的
generated by the orbiting cloud of gas and dust...
将物质送给年轻的恒星
sending material into the young star.
因为旋转它首先形成一个吸积盘
Because of rotation, it first forms an accretion disk...
犹如飞碟围绕着年轻恒星
which is kind of like a Frisbee spinning around the young star...
喂养 打造着年轻的恒星
feeding, building the young star.
现在这个气体中始终存在着磁场
Now, there's always magnetic fields in all of this gas...
随着圆盘的旋转
and as the disk spins...
物质沿着磁力线堆积 这么说吧
material loads up on the field lines, as we say...
它盘旋而上然后被抛入太空
and it spins and then it's flung out into space.
最终磁力线旋转而出
Eventually, the field lines get bent around...
校准喷射 创造出漂亮而坚实的射流
collimating thejet, creating a nice solid jet column.
除了星际喷射
Along with stellarjets...
星云还会表现出狂野的变种
the galaxy's nebulas display a wild variety...
气泡 冲击波 气柱 甚至高山
of bubbles, shockwaves, pillars, and even mountains.
这些叫做创世群山
These are called the Mountains of Creation...
这个星云经常来对比著名的创造之柱
a nebula often compared to the famous Pillars of Creation...
但是 事实上 要大上10倍
but, in fact, ten times as large.
尽管它们有70光年宽
Though they are seventy light-years across...
这幅图片拍自可见光
this image, taken in visible light...
展现了它们细微的外貌
shows them subtle in appearance.
不过来看看我们通过史匹哲太空望远镜
But see what happens when we look at a picture...
用红外线拍摄的照片的情况
from the Spitzer Space Telescope, which views them in infrared.
红外线是波长比可见光略长的光
lnfrared light is light of a slightly longerwavelength than visible light.
比红光更加红
lt's redder than red light.
我们通常看到的发出红外线的物体 比如我们自己
We commonly see infrared light from objects like us...
温暖但不是极热
that are warm, but not extremely hot.
由于 红外线是温暖的物体发出的
Since infrared light is emitted by anything that is warm...
所以 通常被用来检测热量
it's often used to detect heat.
通过特殊的相机各种温度都可以检测到
ln special cameras, each temperature is detected...
由于红外线我们无法看到
as an infrared color that we can't see...
于是它就被转换成可见光让我们能看到
and then it's translated into a visible color that we can see.
那就是红外线可以利用体温
That's how infrared can use body heat...
来展现某些业余天文学家晚间工作的道理
to reveal some amateur astronomers working in the dark of night...
否则我们将不得不打开灯光来看他们了
when otherwise we'd have to turn on a light to see them at all.
在太空中道理是一样的
ln space, the same principle applies.
这是可见光下的天鹰星云
This is the Eagle Nebula as seen in visible light...
但是史匹哲太空望远镜的红外观察就大为不同了
but the infrared Spitzer Telescope sees it in a much different way...
揭示出一个极热的尘埃区 这里红色的区域
revealing a region of extremely hot dust, seen here in red.
现在你不得不思量究竟是什么使得尘埃这么热的？
Now, you have to ask yourself, what could get dust that hot?
是星云里的恒星吗？不
The stars in the nebula? No.
它们还不够亮 不够热
They're not really bright enough, they're not hot enough...
那么 或许是超新星爆发
but maybe a supernova explosion.
或许是恒星的猝死
Maybe the violent death of a star.
超新星会发出巨大的冲击波
A supernova would send out a massive shockwave...
有可能产生深远的影响
which might have a profound impact...
因为 天鹰星云是创造之柱的所在地
because the Eagle Nebula is home to the Pillars of Creation.
对于创造之柱来说看上去并不很好
Now, for the Pillars, it doesn't look very good.
接下来的情况是爆发恒星发出的超新星冲击波
What's going to happen is that supernova shockwave...that's expanding out from the exploding star...
迟早会击中创造之柱
sooner or later is going to hit those Pillars.
一旦击中创造之柱就会将其蒸发
And when it hits the Pillars, it's going to evaporate them...
它们会消失
and they're going to be destroyed...
留下目前正在创造之柱背后形成的恒星
leaving the stars that are currently forming in the Pillars behind...
而所有那些漂亮的气体尘埃 也就是
but all that gas and dust in those beautiful, you know...
柱状的东西都将消失殆尽
pillar-like shapes, they're going to go, just disappear.
揭示著名的创造之柱命运的红外线
The infrared that reveals the fate of the famous Pillars...
只不过是天文学家光线工具箱里的一件工具
is only one tool in the astronomer's light box...
但是 星云可以通过各种光线来观察
but the nebulas can be seen in light of all kinds...
拨开迷雾 揭示它们一直保持的秘密
stripping away shrouds that keep their secrets otherwise hidden forever.
在充满光线的宇宙里
ln a universe filled with light...
天文学家已经学会了观察恒星
astronomers have learned to look at the stars...
通过分析形形色色的光
by analyzing light of different kinds...
诸如 来自史匹哲太空望远镜的红外图像
such as the infrared images from the Spitzer Space Telescope.
红外线只是电磁波谱中的一段
lnfrared is only one region on the electromagnetic spectrum...
电磁波谱-我们用来测量各种辐射波长的
an immense scale we use to measure the wavelengths...
一个庞大序列
of all kinds of radiation.
一头是波长最长的射电波
At one end are radio waves with the longest wavelengths.
另一头是最短的伽玛射线
At the other end are gamma rays with the shortest.
中间的其他波段中包括可见光
ln between are the other bands, including visible light...
只占整个很小的一部分 真是难以想象
which is such a tiny fraction of the whole, it's difficult to imagine.
可见光谱有多短？
How small is the visible spectrum?
如果你用一卷电影胶片
lfyou had a reel of movie film...
来代表整个电磁波谱
representing the entire electromagnetic spectrum...
可以展开2500英里 从加利福尼亚到阿拉斯加
stretching 2,500 miles from California to Alaska...
包括可见光谱的那一段
the section containing the visible spectrum...
就介于中间的某个位置上 华盛顿大学附近
would fall somewhere in the middle, near the University ofWashington.
这一帧就是整个可见光谱
This frame is the whole visible spectrum.
这就是2000多英里带子中的一帧
lt is one frame in over 2,000 miles of tape...
就是肉眼能看到的一切
and it's everything that the human eye can see.
这一帧的重要之处
The importance of this frame...
在于恒星发出的几乎所有的光线
is that stars emit almost all of their light...
都在这部分光谱里
in this part of the spectrum.
尽管光线是看得见的
And even though the light is visible...
但是 它依然包括了隐藏的工具来帮助我们探索星云
it still contains hidden tools, helping us to explore nebulas...
实现我们人眼无法完成的事情
in ways that our eyes cannot do entirely on their own.
秘密在于光谱本身
The secrets are in the spectrum itself.
这个灯泡发出的可见光是
The visible light in this lamp comes from hydrogen gas...
氢气被电流激发形成了发光的等离子体
excited by electricity to form a glowing plasma...
类似于星云里的情况
similar to what happens in a nebula.
通过衍射光栅来观察灯泡
By viewing the lamp through a diffraction grating...
我们可以将光分成光谱上的三条窄条
we can split the light up into three narrow lines on the spectrum...
光的虚拟指纹 是氢独有的
a virtual fingerprint of light, unique to hydrogen alone.
在光谱中你可以看到三个特征
So in the spectrum, you see three features.
这个红色
One is red...
这个淡蓝
one is a light blue...
那个是深蓝
and the other is a deep blue.
这种波长模式绝对是氢独有的
This pattern ofwavelengths is absolutely unique to hydrogen...
是没办法将星云光谱里的氢与其他元素混淆的
and there's no way to confuse hydrogen...in the spectrum of a nebula with any other element.
就像是篮球赛场上的观众
lt's like the crowd at our basketball game.
欢呼的人群实际上是由个别球迷组成的
The cheering mass is actually made up of individual fans...
每个人都有自己独特的声音
each with his or her own distinctive voice...
声音清晰可辨
voices you could make out clearly...
只要你有区分的手段
ifyou had a way to isolate them.
区分星云里各种元素的光谱线
lsolating the individual spectral lines of the elements within nebulas...
已经让天文学家确实值得为我们星系的
has allowed astronomers to create images truly worthy...
这些胜景创作图像
of these tourist attractions of our galaxy.
通过用所谓的窄带滤波器来对照线条
By using what are called narrow-band filters...corresponding to single lines...
天文学家给了我们另一个观察事物的方法
astronomers have given us anotherway of seeing things...
那是我们自己所无法看到的
we can't see by ourselves.
哈勃望远镜拍摄创造之柱时
When the Hubble Telescope photographed the Pillars of Creation...
利用一个滤镜来分离氢元素最亮的红线
it used one filter to isolate hydrogen's brightest red line...
用另一个滤镜来分离硫元素更亮的红线
another to isolate sulfur's even redder line...
用第三个滤镜来捕捉氧元素的蓝绿线条
and a third to capture oxygen's line of blue green.
图像专家佐尔坦·莱沃伊
lmage specialist Zoltan Levay...
将各部分汇总成一张全彩图像
assembles the components into a full color image...
揭示出的东西超过了各部分的总和
that reveals more than the sum of its parts.
通过滤镜拍摄的星云照片
By taking images of the nebula through a filter...
分离了特定元素的光
that isolates the light of a particular element...
我们看到了元素在整个星云里的分布
we are seeing the distribution of that element throughout this nebula.
然而更大程度上
But to a larger extent...
我们要观察星云里物理状态的变化情况
we're seeing how the physical conditions vary across a nebula.
如果氢 氧 硫的线条合并成全彩
lf the true colors of hydrogen, oxygen, and sulfur lines were combined...
那么 创造之柱的图像看上去会是这样的
the image of the Pillars would look something like this.
然而 哈勃团队将每个元素
But the Hubble team translates each element...
都转换成光的三基色之一
into one of light's primary colors.
氧的蓝绿色指定为蓝色
Oxygen's blue green is assigned to blue.
氢的红色指定为绿色
Hydrogen's red is assigned to green.
硫类似于氢的颜色 被指定为红色
And sulfur, similar to hydrogen in color, is assigned to red.
有时称为伪彩色
Sometimes called false color...
图像会优于其本来面目
the image is a better display of material reality.
这就是我提出的将代表色
This l would refer to as representative color...
来作为我们构图的手段
the way we've constructed this image.
颜色可能没有反应出我们所见到的同样的颜色
The colors may not appear the same as the colors we would see...
如果我们用肉眼或通过望远镜能看到的话
If we were looking at this with our unaided eyes...or through a telescope...
但是它们表现了所发生的物理过程
but they represent the physical processes that are happening here.
氢 氧 硫滤镜混合的这种方法叫做哈勃调色板
The hydrogen, oxygen, sulfurfilters...as combined this way are known as the Hubble palette...
被广泛应用于星云的各种成像中
which is used widely in nebular photography of all kinds.
它不仅表明了产星星云多姿多彩
lt shows us not only the colorful chaos of star-forming nebulas...
同时 还是恒星死亡之地惊人的画像
but also the striking images of the places where stars die.
这些美轮美奂错综复杂的宝石点缀宇宙
These beautiful, complex gems that dot the cosmos...
标志着恒星的消亡
marking the demise of stars...
称为行星状星云 这是1784年创造的术语
are called planetary nebulas, a term that was coined in 1784.
行星状星云这种天体
Planetary nebulae are objects...
与行星毫不相干 事实明摆着
that have nothing to do with planets, as it turns out.
它们的取名来自威廉·赫歇尔
They get their name from William Herschel...
他最早通过望远镜观察行星状星云
who looked at a planetary nebula for the first time through a telescope...
看到它呈泛绿色圆形
saw that it was round, greenish in color...
使他想起了天王星
and it reminded him of the planet Uranus.
氧的蓝绿色及氢的红色
The blue greens of oxygen and reds of hydrogen...
主导了行星状星云的全彩照片
dominate true color photos of planetary nebulas.
环状星云是个典型的例子
The Ring Nebula is a prime example.
它距离地球2300光年 直径1.3光年
lt is 2,300 light-years from Earth and 1.3 light-years in diameter.
被认为是行星状星云的原型
lt is considered a prototype for planetary nebulas.
然而环状星云的形状
But the shape of the Ring Nebula...
比其它行星状星云来得简单
is simple compared to other planetary nebulas.
惊奇地发现这样的表现
lt's remarkable to realize that displays like these...
伴随着宇宙间几乎每一颗恒星的消亡
accompany the death of nearly every star in the cosmos...
包括50亿年后我们的太阳
including our own Sun in about five billion years.
恒星在生命行将结束时会膨胀
The star swells up near the end of its life.
太阳会撑满半个天空
The Sun will fill half the sky.
日落西山时
When the sun is setting in the west...
太阳的另一部分会在东方冉冉升起
another part of it will be rising in the east...
到了中午整个天空将会被这个通红的天体填满
and at noon, the whole sky will be filled...
把我们烧成陶器
with this bright red object, baking us to porcelain.
此时恒星内部变得狂躁不安
At this point, the inside of the star becomes wildly unstable.
它歇业了 颤抖了
it shutters, and it quakes...
那时其表面非常松散
and at that point, the surface, which is very loosely bound...
会被抛进太空
can be tossed into space.
可以将它看作星际喷嚏的过程
Think of it as a process of stellar sneezing.
外层气体的膨胀伴随着太阳从红巨星
The outer envelope of gas expands as the Sun shrinks from a red giant...
塌缩成炙热的白矮星
to become a hot white dwarf.
矮星的紫外线激发周围的气体
The dwarf's ultraviolet light excites the surrounding gas...
使其发光 犹如产星区里的情况
causing it to glow just as in star-forming regions.
光芒四射会持续数千年才会消失
The brilliant display will last for thousands ofyears before fading away.
太阳在其生命终结时将会表现出何种宇宙图像
Just what kind of cosmic picture the Sun will paint at the end of its life...
几乎难以预料
is nearly impossible to predict.
但是各种行星状星云惊人景象
But witness the astounding variety...
在星系中比比皆是
of planetary nebulas throughout the galaxy.
是什么让个个都灿烂各异？
What makes each one dazzlingly different?
是什么驱使它们的形状高深莫测？
And what engines drive their enigmatic shapes?
我们银河系里估计有一万个行星状星云
There are an estimated 10,000 planetary nebulas in our galaxy...
每个都呈现出恒星独特的死亡方式
each one displaying the death of a star in its own unique way.
尽管每个行星状星云都产生于一个恒星系
Although each planetary nebula is generated by a single star system...
但是它们的个头相比之下还是巨大的
their size in comparison is immense.
行星状星云是庞大的
Planetary nebulas are huge.
如果太阳系放在我的手指间
If l had the solar system between my fingers...
那么行星状星云的半径会大上1000到10000倍
the planetary nebula would be 1,000 to 10,000 times larger in radius.
然而 由于它们距离地球遥远
And yet, because of their great distance from Earth...
多数行星状星云呈现给我们的犹如宇宙间的小斑点
most planetary nebulas appear to us as tiny specks in the cosmos.
行星状星云NGC 2440距离我们4000光年
The distance to the planetary nebula NGC 2440 is 4,000 light-years.
尽管星云本身有整整一光年宽
And although the nebula itself is one full light-year across...
但是其个头 从地球上看
its size, when viewed from Earth...
只有满月宽度的4%
is only four percent as wide as the full Moon.
只有最强大的望远镜才能看清其细节
Only the most powerful telescopes can see it in detail.
外观大小如月球的星云是螺旋星云
A nebula as large as the Moon in apparent size is the Helix Nebula.
但是 还是需要定时曝光照相才能看清全貌
But it still requires a photo time-exposure to be seen at all.
其震撼的形状启迪了一些人将其称为"上帝之眼"
lts stunning form has inspired some people to call it the "Eye of God."
在450光年外
At about 450 light-years away...
是离地球最近的行星状星云
it is among the closest planetary nebulas to Earth.
正因为这样它一直被认真的研究
As such, it has been studied intensely.
这张相片来自哈勃太空望远镜
This photo from the Hubble Space Telescope...
是制作得最详尽的天文图像之一
is one of the most detailed astronomical images ever made.
在其所揭示的惊奇之中
Among the surprises it reveals...
是星云内部有些奇怪的轮辐状的节点
are strange spoke-like knots inside the nebula.
它们称其为彗星节点
They call them cometary knots...
或许是认为它们来自这颗恒星周围的古老的彗星
thinking maybe they're originally from old comets around this star...
然而事实上这其实是星光与气体的自然互动
when, in fact, it's really a natural interaction...of the starlight with the gas.
在星光射出时像是在轰击气体
As the starlight comes out, it sort of shocks the gas...
就像是在火上泼冷水
kind of like throwing cold water on a hot fire...
造成气体缠绕破碎
and it causes the gas to sort of curl and fragment.
行星状星云表现出的灿烂色彩是伪装
The brilliant colors seen in photos of planetary nebulas are deceiving.
如果飞船靠近螺旋星云中央的恒星
lf a spaceship were near the central star...
举个例子
of the Helix Nebula, for instance...
发光的气体是根本看不见的 因为太稀薄了
the glowing gas would be practically invisible because it's so thin.
只有加速从行星状星云外围经过
Only by speeding to the planetary nebula's outer reaches...
景色才会有所变化
would the view start to change.
我们必须穿越约1000个太阳系的半径
We would have to travel for about a thousand solar system radii...
才能看到行星状星云里的发光气体
before we began to see the glow of the gases...in the planetary nebula itself.
这些看上去很像我们在地球上看到的极光
And these would look a lot like the Aurora...that we see here on Earth.
色彩美不胜收
The colors would be beautiful.
此后不久我们将结束星云的穿行
Then shortly after that, we would finish flying through the nebula...
出没于太空深处
and we would be out in the depths of space.
回看星云 色彩更为清晰
Looking back on the nebula, the colors are more apparent.
气体是在太稀薄了难以看到
The gas is otherwise too thin to be seen...
除非 我们能够看透数十亿英里后的外壳
unless we're looking through its entire envelope...
就如我们现在这样
billions of miles thick, as we are now.
即使 到了此时 我们还是需要得到帮助
But even at this point, we need help.
我们的眼睛预计看到的是氢元素的红色
Our eyes see the expected hydrogen red...
但是 有更多的颜色显现出来 结构变得更加清晰
but more colors show up, and the structure becomes clearer...
只要我们的飞船用上哈勃调色板
if our spacecraft applies the Hubble palette to ourview.
不过我们看到的星云受限于我们的位置
Still, ourview of the nebula is limited by our position.
就像从地球上观察一样
Just as we do from Earth...
我们只能从一个方向进行观察
we're seeing it from only one direction.
它看上去就像是拉长的圆环
lt looks like an elongated ring.
然而我们的飞船快速围绕星云
But our spacecraft speeds around the nebula...
从另一个角度看会有很大的不同
and we realize that from another angle, it looks very different.
不是一个气体环 甚至球状
lt is not a ring of gas, or even a sphere...
而是两个分开交叉的盘子
but two distinct intersecting disks...
可能缘自中央恒星在其生命周期行将终结时
possibly caused by the central star discharging gas...
在两个不同的阶段
in two separate phases at different times...
以不同的时间将气体排放出来
near the end of its life cycle.
围绕着行星状星云形状的问题
The questions surrounding the shapes of planetary nebulas...
是整个天文学中最令人困扰的
are among the most perplexing in all of astronomy.
来看一下行星状星云的其它形状
Let's take a look at some of the shapes of planetary nebulae.
其形状从球形如柠檬片星云
They range from round like the Lemon Slice Nebula...
到椭圆形如螺线图星云等好多好多
to elliptical like the Spirograph Nebula and many others...
以至到极端的例子如蚂蚁星云
to extreme cases like the Ant Nebula...
双鱿鱼星云 又称M2-9
and the Double Squid Nebula, otherwise known as M2-9.
由于恒星脱胎于球状
Since a star starts out as a sphere...
你可能预计其临终的气体
you might expect its dying gas...
会形成球状的行星状星云
to produce a spherical planetary nebula.
但 实际上 只有10%的行星状星云具有这种形状
But, in fact, only ten percent of planetary nebulas have this shape.
所有的动力中 隐藏在外来因素背后
Among the engines behind more exotic forms...
是来自层层气体的星际风
are the stellarwinds from different layers of gas...
是恒星在死亡过程的不同时段
thrown out by the star at different times in its death cycle...
以不同速度抛出的
and at different speeds.
你看到的是一套组合风
And what you get is an interacting set ofwinds...
内部的风之间相互撞击
winds colliding with otherwinds from the inside.
这是塑造星云的过程
That's a process that sculpts the nebula...
帮助形成了其有趣的形状
and helps to give it its interesting shapes.
最具魅力的行星状星云
The most intriguing of the planetary nebulas...
就是那些双极状的
are those with bipolar shapes.
这些怪物中的神秘力量
Mysterious forces within these strange objects...
把发光的气体射出喷射
cause glowing gas to shoot out injets...
使人联想起恒星在诞生过程中的星际喷射
reminiscent of the stellarjets from stars in the process of being born.
这两个极其类似的现象怎么会
How could two so similar phenomena...
同时发生在恒星的诞生和死亡的呢？
happen at both the beginning and the end of stellar life?
喷射是无处不有的天文现象
Jets are a ubiquitous phenomena in astronomy.
所有这些喷射的共同点
What all thesejets have in common...
就是都存在着积吸盘
is the presence of an accretion disk...
那是一团旋转的气体
which is rotating gas...
旋转气体中存在磁场
magnetic fields in the rotating gas...
当物质流过积吸盘时
and as material flows through the accretion disk...
被拉进磁力线
and loads on the field lines...
就被吹入太空
it gets blown back out into space.
但是垂死的恒星没有一个物质会掉进去的圆盘
But a dying star doesn't have a disk of material falling into it.
也就是除非是成双成对
That is, unless it's a part of a binary pair...
两颗恒星互相围绕
two stars orbiting around each other.
双星在宇宙间是很普遍的
Binary pairs are very common in the universe.
两颗恒星相互围绕时
As the two stars rotate around each other...
其中一颗会将物质送给另一颗
one of the stars is giving up mass to the other.
物质从一颗流向另一颗
Material flows from one star to the other...
就形成了一个积吸盘
and you form an accretion disk.
磁场就出现在那个积吸盘里
Magnetic fields appear in that accretion disk...
物质被吹走就如其它案例那样
and material is blown off it just like in the other cases as well.
行星状星云表现了整个空间的
Planetary nebulas represent the normal processes...
恒星死亡的正常过程
of star death throughout space.
然而 宇宙间存在着极不正常的巨人恒星
But there are giant stars in the universe...that are farfrom normal.
它们在巨大的爆炸中结束自己的生命
They conclude their lives in massive explosions...
通常星云留下的是它们遭遇的
and, often, the nebulas left behind are the only clues...
惨烈终结的唯一的线索
tojust how they met theirviolent ends.
1054年一颗巨大的恒星爆发
ln the year1054, a massive star blew up...
距离太阳系有6300光年
6,300 light-years away from the solar system.
从地球上看似空中最亮的一颗新星
From the Earth, it appeared as a new star...the most brilliant in the sky.
比金星亮10倍
Ten times brighter than Venus...
大白天能看到有29天
it was visible in broad daylight for 29 days.
它被中国的天文学家注意到了
lt was noted by Chinese astronomers...
或许还有新墨西哥的阿纳萨齐人
and perhaps the Anasazi of New Mexico...
在他们的岩画中也看到了
as seen in one of their petroglyphs.
它的消失与出现一样突然
lt faded away almost as quickly as it appeared...
如今 我们只能通过望远镜看到它了
and today we can see it only through telescopes.
然而它留下的东西蔚为壮观
But what's left of it is spectacular.
1000年后我们将它称为蟹状星云
A thousand years later, we call it the Crab Nebula...
其是一种星云叫做超新星残骸
one of a variety of nebulas known as supernova remnants.
超新星残骸其实是扩展的残片云
Supernova remnants are essentially the expanding debris clouds...
来自巨大恒星的星际爆发
from the stellar explosion of a really massive star.
是大质量恒星在其生命终结时的终极爆发
lt's the death explosion of that massive star at the end of its life.
超新星残骸类似于行星状星云
Supernova remnants are something like planetary nebulas...
都来自恒星的终结
in that each results from the death of a star.
在恒星首次演变成行星状星云时
As a starfirst evolves to become a planetary nebula...
从其表面极其缓慢地喷出的稠密的物质
it ejects dense mass from its surface very slowly.
这不是爆发 只是喷发
This is not an explosion, it's just an ejection.
超新星简单多了 就是爆发
A supernova is much simpler. lt's just an explosion.
一切就发生在几秒钟里
Everything happens in seconds.
我们所看到的它周围的星云
And the nebula that we see around it...
就是残留的碎片
is the shrapnel that still remains.
爆发的冲击波轰击周围的物质使其发光
The light show comes from the explosion's shockwave...smashing into the surrounding material and causing it to glow.
其原理得到戏剧性的例证发生在2004年
The principle was dramatically illustrated...as it actually happened in 2004...
当时哈勃太空望远镜捕捉到了这个冲击波
when the Hubble Space Telescope caught this shockwave...
在轰击超新星残骸里的气环
striking a ring of gas in the remnant of a supernova...
它爆发于1987年16万光年外
that exploded 160,000 light-years away in 1987.
言归正传蟹状星云仍然是最有名的超新星残骸
Closer to home, the Crab Nebula remains the most famous...of all supernova remnants.
通过望远镜研究了300年
Studied through telescopes for 300 years...
其中隐藏着一个秘密直到1968年才揭秘
it contains a secret buried inside, undiscovered until 1968.
其最中心是一颗脉冲星 每秒钟旋转30次
At the very center is a pulsar, spinning at thirty times per second.
脉冲星是旋转的中子星
A pulsar is a spinning neutron star...
其密度大到一茶勺重达10亿吨
so dense that one teaspoon of it would weigh a billion tons.
蟹状星云中的那个只有18英里的直径
The one inside the Crab Nebula is just eighteen miles across...
却比太阳还重
and weighs more than our Sun.
它快速旋转 但因速度放缓而在丢失能量
lt's spinning fast, but losing energy by gradually slowing down.
其转动能正在转移到气体里
And the energy of its rotation is being transferred into the gas...
事实上 星云里的大量辐射
and, in fact, much of the radiation in that nebula...
就是由放慢的脉冲星来推动的
is powered by the slowdown of the pulsar.
那种辐射看上去就像是阴森的蓝光
That radiation is seen as the eerie blue glow...
处于蟹状星云中央
in the center of the Crab Nebula.
其原因在于 电子接近光速运动
lt is generated by electrons moving at near the speed of light...
经过脉冲星的磁场所致
through the magnetic fields of the pulsar.
然而 不止是发出蓝光
But there is more than blue glow.
最近的太空照片显示那个磁场
Recent space photos reveal that the magnetic fields...
正在星云中央搅动
are stirring up the center of the nebula.
你可以看到脉冲星传出的涟漪
You see little ripples emanating out from the pulsar.
不错的比喻是
lt's not a bad analogy...
把磁场比作拉长的橡皮圈
to think of magnetic fields as stretched rubber bands...
你拉它时
and when you pluck them...
会引起扰动 它只管前行
you cause a disturbance that works its way through them.
不知怎么回事一路往前
And that's what's going on somehow or another.
细节超乎想象
The details are beyond us.
但是 我们能看到现象 非常清晰
But we can see the phenomenon, and it's quite clear.
形成蟹状星云的恒星的死亡
The death of the star that formed the Crab Nebula...
是星系生命周期的组成部分
is part of the life cycle of the galaxy.
气体排入太空
The gas expelled into space...
成为了超新星残骸和行星状星云
as supernova remnants and planetary nebulas...
又回到了星际介质
returns to the interstellar medium...
成为了新一代恒星的原料
where it becomes raw material for future generations of stars.
这个过程不能永远持续下去
This process cannot go on forever...
因为氢气量有限
because we have a finite amount of hydrogen gas.
迟早会耗尽点亮星星 使之闪烁的氢和氦
Sooner or later, you use up most of the hydrogen and helium...which light up the stars, and the stars blink out.
你现在看到的银河系
When you look at the Milky Way today...
97%的物质在恒星里
ninety-seven percent of its mass is in stars...
3%在气体中
three percent is left in gas.
在恒星形成的过程中
And as starformation proceeds...
蓄水池在不断地降低
that reservoir is going to go down and down and down.
当然 恒星形成会放慢 因为气体
Certainly, starformation will slow down because this gas...
很难离开那个范围 姑且这样说吧
is just harder to get out of the ground, as it were.
然而 天文学家利用绿岸射电望远镜
But astronomers, using the Green Bank Radio Telescope...
最近发现了一个气源
have recently discovered one source of gas...
就在银河系外的大团星云里
in a massive cloud outside the Milky Way.
有趣的是这个星云
The very interesting thing about this cloud...
被称为史密斯云
which has been called Smith's Cloud...
非常庞大
is that it's very massive.
其中的气体尘埃是太阳质量的100万倍
lt's got about a million times the mass of the Sun in it of gas and dust.
现在这个星云正冲着银河系而来
Well, this cloud is headed right toward the Milky Way.
在2000到4000万年里它将会于我们相撞
And in 20 to 40 million years, it's going to collide with us.
会产生压力 冲击波
Now, that's going to create a pressure, a shockwave.
在它碰撞银河系时
And it may set off a generation of hundreds of new stars...
可能引出数百颗新一代新星
when it collides with the Milky Way.
由于史密斯云里的气体在碰撞中被压缩
As the gas in Smith's Cloud is compressed by the collision...
全新的产星星云将点亮星系
a brand-new star-forming nebula will light up the galaxy...
宇宙的生命周期将得以延续
and the lifecycle of the universe will continue.
从长远来看 不管怎样 没有足够的史密斯云
ln the long term, however, there aren't enough Smith's Clouds...
来维持这个过程的继续
to keep the process going...
星云将会逐渐消失
and nebulas will gradually disappear.
宇宙已有约140亿岁了
The universe is about 14 billion years old...
1000亿年后回看银河系
and come back in a hundred billion years...and look at the Milky Way...
巨大明亮的恒星将不可能再形成了
the big, bright, massive stars can't form anymore.
留下的只是古老的恒星残骸
All that's left are the ancient remnants of stars...
那是很久以前所形成的
that formed in the long past.
是个沉闷 乏味之地
lt's a dull place, a very dull place.
我们生活在宇宙岁月中一段激动人心的时段里
We live in an exciting time in the era of the universe...
恒星尚未燃尽
before stars burn out...
形成新恒星和行星的新材料水库尚未干涸
and the reservoir of new material is gone...for forming new stars and planets.
这是个优越的时段
lt's a privileged time.
这个时段天空依然充满着光辉
A time when the sky still remains filled...
有大猎户星云
with the lights of the great Orion Nebula...
创造之柱
the Pillars of Creation...
上帝之眼
and the Eye of God...
大自然的每一个小奇迹
each one a small marvel of nature...
存在于广袤的宇宙间
in the vast expanse of the universe.
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing